In this video, we will be talking about
total
internal reflection. So,
as we have learned before, light refracts,
and
it's going to bend towards the medium.
But there is a case when light goes from
the
higher index medium to a lower index
medium,
for example from this glass of water to
air,
and the incident angle is so large that
the
light reflects back. And that is because
it
would require sine theta to be bigger than
one,
which is impossible. So, there are two
conditions
for total internal reflection. The first
condition
is that the light must go from a higher
medium
to a lower medium. The
second condition is that the incident
angle
must be greater than the critical angle.
And the critical angle is the incident
angle
that makes the reflected ray travel along
the
boundary, which I will talk about later.
But all you need to know is that the
incident
angle is bigger than the critical angle.
So, what does the critical angle mean?
Well, let's say you have light that
reflects
towards the medium.
And it is so that an angle goes all the
way
like this. And it's going to refract.
It's not going to go past. It's not going
to
reflect. It's going to go exactly at the
middle.
So basically, theta 2 in this case would
be
equal to 90. Because this would be the
medium.
And the critical angle is this angle over
here.
That makes the theta 2 equal to 90.
And from Snell's law, we can actually
derive
the critical angle. Because n1 sine theta
critical,
which is what we want to find, will be
equal
to n2 sine 90.
Because n2 is 90 when we have the critical
angle.
So sine theta critical equals n2 over n1.
And sine 90 is just 1. And this is what we
have.
Also, n1 must be greater than n2 because
sine
theta can't be equal to more than 1.
And now, let's have a quick example about
this
critical angle. If light travels from
glass,
which typically has an index of refraction
of
1.5, to air, which has an index of
refraction
to 1.00, then the critical angle, sine of
theta
critical, would just be equal to that of
air
over that of glass. Because it's traveling
from
air to glass. So it would be nA over nG,
which
is 1 over 1.5, which is 0.667.
So when we solve it, sine theta C, equals
0.667,
theta C would be equal to 41.8 degrees.
So that is our critical angle.
Our critical angle is 41.8 degrees here.
Since in order to have internal
reflection,
theta 1 must be equal to the critical
angle.
Any incident angle greater than 41.8
degrees
will give total inflection.
So for example, if we copy this diagram
and
we pretend this is our diagram, then in
order
for this to occur, our critical angle
would
need to be 41.8 degrees.
However, if we want it to reflect, then
the
incident angle must be greater than 41.8
degrees.
If we want it to refract, then it must be
less
than 41.8 degrees. So we can know a lot of
things
from the critical angle. If it's higher
than
the critical angle, then total internal
reflection
occurs. Otherwise, if it's lower than the
critical
angle, it refracts.
So the key takeaways are that the
critical angle is when it doesn't refract
nor
reflect. And also, be very, very familiar
with
Snell's law because you're going to use it
in
many, many different applications. And if
you
forget something, you can always look at
Snell's
law and you will probably remember it
because
you can use numbers to try and figure
things
out with this law. And yeah, total
internal
reflection is also used in a lot of real
world
applications, of course. You have to know
this
for grade 10 science and IB, probably not
AP,
but just know that some examples include
fiber
optics, binoculars, and also it's what
causes
the sparkle in a lot of jewels, such as
diamonds,
because they have a very, very high index
of
refraction. Which, in turn, gives small
critical
angles. So light is easily reflected.
That's all for today's video and I hope
you
enjoyed. Thank you!